Now, I've been around long enough to
know exactly what that look on your face
means. It means that you want to talk
about the causes and effects of the
massive 19th century economic
restructuring of the United States that
we call the market revolution. I know
it's like I'm in your head. Anyway, that
market revolution ain't going to talk
about itself. So, if you're ready to get
them brain cows milked, let's get to it.
Okay, so in this period, metric
buttloadads of Americans migrated west
in order to take advantage of the cheap
and abundant farmland over there, not to
mention the growing cities like St.
Louis and Cincinnati. But in
establishing their farms in the
frontier, they found themselves
increasingly isolated from the markets
that dominated the east coast. And that
meant that they were unable to buy goods
that they needed for their households
and they found it difficult to ship
their excess agricultural goods to sell
on distant markets. And as a 21st
century high schooler, I know you
relate. Anyway, in this period, a flurry
of new technologies and the rapid
development of industrial manufacturing
started to solve those problems. It was
called the market revolution and it
describes a development in which the
relationship between producers and
consumers became the primary economic
element of American society. Now, what
in the actual fresh heck does that mean?
Well, think about it this way. Before
the market revolution, the vast majority
of Americans lived on small farms and
produced whatever they needed to survive
themselves. And whatever they could not
make or grow for themselves, they either
bought from a local store or bartered
with their neighbors. But after the
market revolution, more and more people
bought and sold on the market what they
needed to survive. Now to be clear at
this point the US was still primarily
agrarian but manufacturing and commerce
was becoming more and more prominent and
so the big effect of this revolution was
twofold. First it boosted the national
economy by tying together the various
regional economies making them more and
more dependent on one another. Second it
encouraged regional economic
specialization or to say in a way you
might actually understand each region
was encouraged to produce what they were
best at producing and then import
whatever other goods they needed from
other regions. So, for example, the
South was really good at growing cotton
by the metric buttload. The North was
really good at manufacturing
mass-produced goods, and the West was
really good at growing food. And so, as
the national economy was becoming more
integrated, that meant that each region
needed to lean more and more into their
own specialty since everyone depended on
everyone else. You smell what I'm
stepping in? Good. Because before I tell
you about some of the new technologies
that enabled the market revolution, I
need to tell you about how to induce a
revolution in your A push grade. I see
what you did there. Anyway, if you want
help getting an A in your class and a
five on your exam in May, then you
should probably check out my A Push
Heimler review guide. It's going to help
you study for your class exams and your
national exams as fast as possible. And
it's got loads of material to help you
do that. So, if that's something that
you're into, then check that link in the
description. Okay. Now, I know that
you're itching to understand the causes
of that great confilration of economic
interconnectedness and interdependence.
Again, I know it's astonishing how well
I have my fingers on the pulse of 21st
century youth culture. So, let me
explain it up for you real quick. At the
most general level, the market
revolution occurred because the process
of industrial manufacturing became more
efficient and organized. Now, by
efficient, I mean that goods could be
produced a lot faster and in greater
quantities than ever before. And by
organized, I mean that the dizzying
array of manufactured and industrial
goods could be reliably transported both
within the United States and to
international markets. So, let's get
some examples of technologies that made
production more efficient. And then
we'll consider developments that made
production more organized. First,
production was made more efficient
because of new technologies, and I'm
only going to mention a handful. And
first, let's talk about interchangeable
part. Now, this was the brainchild of
our boy Eli Whitney, of whom I'll have
more to say in a moment. So, after
having received a government contract to
manufacture guns, Whitney decided to
massproduce them with machines instead
of making them by hand. You see, the
problem with handmade guns is that if a
trigger, for example, goes bad, then the
whole gun is broken because that was the
only trigger that would fit on that
particular gun. But Whitney decided to
manufacture each part of the gun
separately and with machined precision.
And that meant that every part of the
gun was compatible with any other gun.
Did your trigger break? Well, here's a
new one made to the exact specifications
you need. Did your shooting tube get
bent? Well, here's a new one. I'm sure
it's not called a shooting tube, but I
don't know anything about guns. You you
get the point. All the individual parts
were made with precision by machines,
and that meant the parts were
interchangeable. And not only that, but
equally important, guns made with
interchangeable parts were way cheaper
to massproduce. And so, other
manufacturers grew a question mark over
their head and started wondering if that
works for guns, would it also work for
chairs or shirts or whatever? And the
answer is a resounding heck yes. And so,
Whitney essentially created a blueprint
for a more efficient process for the
mass production of goods. and it became
known as the American system of
manufacturing. And in its essence, this
system could be boiled down to two
components. First was the factory, which
housed water powered machines, though
later they would be steam powered, but
I'll get to that in a moment. And the
second element was a new division of
labor in which small groups of unskilled
workers fed raw materials to the
machines to keep them running, which
made goods cheaper and faster to make.
And that would be the model that would
fill up the horizon of American
manufacturing during this period. Okay.
The second technology that made
production more efficient was the steam
engine. As I just mentioned, the
machines in all the earliest factories
were water powered, a requirement that
meant that factories had to be built
next to running water. But a steam
engine could power machines by burning
coal and heating water. And that meant
the factories could be built in more
strategic locations in proximity to
markets or raw materials or boats. Okay.
Now, third, let me tell you about three
agricultural technologies that
revolutionized farming. First was the
steel plow invented by John Deere. So
basically, many farmers who migrated
west encountered soil that was real
difficult to plow with traditional
wooden tools. But in 1837, John Deere
created a lightweight steel plow that
was able to break the Midwestern soil at
a much faster pace, thus making planting
way more efficient. And the second
invention here was the cotton gin,
invented by Eli Whitney, which I hope
you remember was the interchangeable
parts guy. Now, this was his first major
invention, and it sped up the process of
separating cotton seeds from cotton
fibers, and that created the conditions
for southern cotton production to go
wild. And then third, we had the
mechanical reaper. So if the cotton gin
revolutionized southern agriculture, it
was Cyrus McCormack's mechanical reaper
that revolutionized western agriculture
and led to greater productivity for the
farmers who specialized in food
production for the United States. With
this machine, a single farmer could
essentially do the harvesting work of
five farmers who used hand tools. And so
the point to remember here is this.
These new technologies created the
conditions for agricultural productivity
and efficiency to skyrocket. Therefore,
as machines expanded the abilities of
farmers to plant and harvest faster than
ever, they saw more and more land on
which to plant, which in turn led to an
increasing commercialization of
agriculture in the West. Okay, so those
are a few of the technologies that
increase the efficiency of production.
But you're also going to need to know
exactly how the market revolution was
fostered by better organization. And
again, by organization, we're talking
about all the processes by which goods
were made and transferred to markets.
Okay. Now, the granddaddy of all the
organizing principles of the market
revolution was the introduction of the
factory. Now, I know I already mentioned
this when I talked about Eli Whitney,
but Whitney didn't establish the factory
as a system in America. No, that honor
goes to Samuel Slater, and he was kind
of a saucy guy. So, let me tell you
about it. So, he was a supervisor in a
British factory who secretly immigrated
to the United States in 1789 because he
heard that investors in America were
interested in building factories on the
British model. And so, having memorized
as much as he could about British
factory schematics, Slater offered his
services to a Rhode Island investor who
thereafter designed a textile factory,
and it worked brilliantly. The factory
produced yarn at a rapid industrial pace
which was then sold to artisans who wo
the yarn into finished clothing. And
this system significantly increased the
productivity of cloth production in the
region and created a more organized
manner in which to sell goods to
consumers. Okay. Second, I need to tell
you about the invention of the
telegraph. So in 1844, Samuel Morse
invented this device which harnessed
short electrical signals to communicate
at a distance. And I don't think I can
overestimate just what a big problem
this solved. You see, as more and more
miles of telegraph wire were hung,
distance cities and markets were able to
communicate with each other almost
instantly. And that led to an even
greater interdependence of America's
increasingly complex regional business
partnerships. Okay. Now, the last piece
of the puzzle that helps us understand
how the market revolution occurred is
everyone's favorite. That's right, you
know it and you love it, infrastructure.
See, you can massproduce goods in a real
organized and efficient manner, but if
you don't have a way to transport those
goods to people who will buy them, then
ain't no revolution happening to nobody.
So, here's where I tell you that in
order to further foster regional
economic interdependence, both the
federal and state governments sponsor
the construction of transportation
systems. And I hope that rings a bell
from a couple videos ago because all
this is happening in the context of
Henry Clay's American system. Anyway,
here I only want to talk about three of
the most important transportation
developments. First, we have the
construction of roads. For example, the
Lancaster turnpike in Pennsylvania was
the first major engineered road
constructed in the United States. Now,
the Pennsylvania state government
couldn't afford to pay for this
fancymancy road and so their legislature
went ahead and passed a policy approving
the road and then a private company
built it and earned revenue through
tolls. But when it was done, the road
connected urban Philadelphia with
Pennsylvania's abundant farmland in
Lancaster, which was about 60 mi away,
drastically cutting the cost of
transporting weed and other crops
between the two regions. And then the
Cumberland Road deserves an honorable
mention here as well. But since I talked
about in a previous video, I'll keep it
short. This road was notable not only
for its length, which connected several
states, but also because it was a rare
interstate road project that was
conceived of and paid for by the federal
government. Okay. Now, the second major
category of new infrastructure was the
development of canals. Now, a canal, in
case you don't know, is a river made by
humans. You see, shipping goods on water
was always the best way to deliver them
to distant markets. But, as it turns
out, sometimes the rivers don't go where
you want them to go. So, what do you do?
Well, you go ahead and dig a new river.
Now, during the first part of the 19th
century, the US went canal crazy and
started building them dang near
everywhere they could. But the canal
that set off that craze was the Eerie
Canal in New York that linked Albany to
Buffalo. It was completed in 1825 and
was a real success. The canal
facilitated water-based trade across New
York State, and that led to New York
City becoming one of the US's biggest
and most profitable commercial cities.
And finally, we need to talk about the
growth of railroads. Now, as excited as
everyone was about the canal boom, by
the 1830s, railroads were offering stiff
competition as the most efficient means
of regional economic interconnection.
You see, thanks to steam powered
locomotives, goods and passengers could
be transported quickly and cheaply
across the United States. And that both
caused the market revolution and further
fostered it as well. But I do need to
mention one thing you'll need to
remember. Many of these infrastructure
projects I mentioned did a great job of
connecting the north and west while
leaving the southern states fewer
opportunities to take advantage of the
increasing interconnection. Okay, the
last thing I need to tell you about is a
couple of Supreme Court cases that
facilitated the conditions for the
market revolution as well. First, let's
consider McCullik v. Maryland, which was
decided in 1819. Now, I talked about
this in a previous video in the context
of Chief Justice John Marshall's
attempts to strengthen the federal
government at the expense of state
government. Basically, the state of
Maryland tried to levy attacks on the
local branch of the national bank and
the court put the kibash on that
practice. But in the context of the
market revolution, this decision
enhanced the federal government's
ability to create favorable conditions
for explosive market growth. Things like
stable currency in the regulation of
interstate commerce. Second, let's
consider Gibbons v. Ogden, which was
decided in 1824. Essentially, the court
struck down a New York state law that
granted a private company a monopoly on
trade between New York and New Jersey.
In the decision, Marshall pointed out
that the Constitution granted the power
to regulate interstate commerce to the
federal government and not to state
governments. And so with decisions like
these and a handful of others, the court
created fertile conditions for the
spectacular national economic growth
that came in the market revolution.
Okay, you can click here to watch my
other videos for unit 4, or you can
click here to grab my A Push Himler
review guide, which is going to help you
get an A in your class and a five on
your exam in May. And I'm glad you came
around, and I'll catch you on the
flip-flop. Himler out.